<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The YnoGuy</title>
    <description>Wine+Software by Bill Langley</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 17:38:40 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 17:38:40 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Neighborly</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-pays-to-have-good-neighbors&quot;&gt;It Pays to Have Good Neighbors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Sonoma County there are over 425 wineries with tasting rooms. In our little pocket of the Russian River Valley there over a dozen within a 5 minute drive of each other. From a tourists perspective, it can be overwhelming. That’s why in each of our “micro” regions we often make recommendations for our customers. They often include some kind of incentive like a 2-for-1 tasting coupon. Regardless of whether they buy wine, we want our customers to appreciate our little niche on the wine map and recommend it to their friends when they return home. If the sales associate is doing their job they will recommend a winery they believe will suit the observed customers tastes. In a tasting room, these are considered qualified leads. If a neighbor has been doing a good job sending leads, some kind of reward is usually in order. Ordinarily, this is a bottle of wine…accompanied by more coupons, of course. This little marketing practice has been going on for years in tasting rooms. Probably without the knowledge of the marketing people upstairs staring at their spreadsheets. Until now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just so happens that one week last summer I received two referrals from a neighbor winery that both led to club signups. For those of you doing the math, that’s a 100% conversion rate! After sending the referrer some love, it suddenly occurred to my marketing software brain these referrals should be recorded in a way that even those upstairs people would understand. It’s no secret that qualified leads increase conversion rates and visa vie sales. So, why don’t we track where these leads are coming from and their performance over time? So naturally, I set to work on building a software solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simple-affordable-useful&quot;&gt;Simple, Affordable, Useful…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/neighborly-charts.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yno Neighborly Dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yno Neighborly Dashboard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…is the credo of Yno Software and I built Neighborly with it in mind. For just $15/month Neighborly provides wineries with the means to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create referrers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create and print custom coupons for each referrer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track resulting referrer sales and conversions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track referred customer sales and conversions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compare referred to non-referrered results over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All directly from within your &lt;a href=&quot;https://commerce7.con&quot;&gt;Commerce7&lt;/a&gt; admin panel. No additional subscription fees or outside websites to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make Yno Neighborly part of your outreach program. Try measuring A/B comparisons with different coupon offers/referrers. For instance, a high-end tour guide might be more interested in shipping or case discounts than 2-for-1 tasting coupons. Neighborly even allows you target individuals in an organization. Perhaps issue one coupon for a restaurant and another for its Somm. The bottom line is Neighborly provides you with measurable results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-pipeline&quot;&gt;In The Pipeline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/neighborly-coupons.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yno Neighborly Printable Coupons&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yno Neighborly Printable Coupons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, Neighborly coupons are a single, generic design. I intend to create brandable coupon templates in the next version that you can make your own. Other than that please let me know other enhancements you think will make Neighborly more valuable to you. I’m always listening!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YnoGuy&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 04:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/introducing-yno-neighborly/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/introducing-yno-neighborly/</guid>
        
        <category>wine software D2C referrals</category>
        
        
        <category>Software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Software</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;real-solutions-for-real-wine&quot;&gt;Real Solutions for Real Wine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am excited to announce that I am back in the wine biz. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynosoftware.com&quot;&gt;Yno Software&lt;/a&gt; is now a business and its first product, &lt;a href=&quot;https://neighborly.wine&quot;&gt;Yno Neighborly&lt;/a&gt;, was just released as an app on &lt;a href=&quot;https://commerce7.com/partners/apps/yno-neighborly/&quot;&gt;Commerce7’s CRM platform&lt;/a&gt;. The Yno Software credo is to develop software specifically for D2C “real wine” producers. These small businesses are near-and-dear to my heart and I hope to help them by producing small, practical apps that will help boost their bottom line without breaking the bank. I call these, “real solutions for real wine”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-real-wine-part&quot;&gt;The Real Wine Part&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been a wine enthusiast all my adult life. Living in the SF Bay Area I’ve had the privilege of touring nearby wine regions, including Napa, Sonoma, and the Santa Cruz mountains. Over the last 40 years I’ve literally watched the CA wine industry explode in front of me. A little over 10 years ago I decided to get in on the ground floor as a wine educator. Tasting rooms are magical places where the wine curious become wine enthusiasts. It’s a unique environment where one can see, feel, and smell how wine is made. What they are experiencing is, IMHO, the making of “real wine”. I made the term up because, surprisingly, there is no other definition. We have craft beer and single barrel whiskey, but no equivalent term for wine. Oh sure, there’s marketing labels like premium and luxury, but they have anything to do with how wine is made. We can’t use the word “craft” because unlike beer and spirits, which are purposely crafted to produce certain styles, in real wine we are trying to avoid manipulation. In order to accomplish this we have to source select local vineyards, pick at exact ripeness, ferment, barrel, and bottle in close proximity, thereby avoiding outside influences as much as possible. The result is what I call real wine. It is not engineered for a specific event, lifestyle, or market. It is just an expression of the environment it comes from where each year brings nuance and discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-real-solutions-part&quot;&gt;The Real Solutions Part&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing. Real wine is hard to make and even harder to sell. The old saying, “if you want to make a million in the wine business start with 10 million” is more true today than ever before. A small winery today finds themselves in a situation where they can’t find distributors (a topic for another blog post), have increased competition, and suffer from declining consumption. So, how does a real wine producer navigate this? Well, there’s lots of advice out there. Most of it is technology based, and, for the last 20 years wineries have been trying to navigate their digital options. As a wine educator and a software engineer I’ve been able to observe this firsthand. In hospitality I’ve seen how lead generation is crucial to conversion rates. In marketing I’ve analyzed e-commerce campaigns and built digital marketing tools. Finally, I worked in wine tech on both business and consumer applications. From all of this experience I have come to the following conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not all wine producers are alike and different segments have very different needs. Think Home Depot vs. Ace Hardware. If Ace followed the same practices as HD they would be out of business by now. The same is true for wine businesses. Constellation and Gallo operate on a completely different level vs. a family-owned winery. There is little one could learn from the other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;E-commerce is a double-edged sword for D2C producers. I expect a lot of pushback on this, but I have seen firsthand results from e-commerce campaigns. Don’t get me wrong EC is an essential sales and marketing tool, but when overused can damage conversion rates. Think about it. Every EC campaign I’ve ever seen contains an offer or discount of some kind. If you’re blasting out discounts every month, why would anyone join your club?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which brings me to my final conclusion. D2C wine producers should be singularly focussed on just one thing…fan acquisition and retention (aka club members).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/just-one-thing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Do just one thing&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;City Slickers | Columbia Pictures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fans, by definition, are customers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who love your story as much as your product&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who will buy your product at any price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who will tell their friends about you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fans are gifts that keep on giving. Once acquired they are relatively inexpensive to retain. They purchase without promotion and boost your reputation in the marketplace. For producers without large marketing budgets, fans are really their only sustainable choice for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wine marketing gurus are saying that technology should play a key role in wine marketing. On this I generally agree, but their solutions are where I take issue. LinkedIn is currently a-buzz with digital marketing solutions like social media engineering, machine learning, AI, and alike. As software engineer, I frankly find these conversations laughable. Because I know firsthand what they require and how much they cost. OpenAI didn’t acquire $500B in private investments so it can sell affordable solutions to D2C wineries. And the long tail benefits won’t be realized for years…if ever. See conclusion #1. These tools are being developed for the big boys, not small D2C producers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real solutions for D2C producers need to be affordable and fan-focused. That’s why I started Yno Software. To build software solutions that will incrementally help D2C wineries acquire and retain fans. That’s what I mean by “real solutions for real wine”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YnoGuy&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 04:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/introducing-yno-software/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/introducing-yno-software/</guid>
        
        <category>wine software D2C</category>
        
        
        <category>Software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Respectfully, the Martini</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;wait-i-thought-this-was-a-wine-blog&quot;&gt;Wait, I thought this was a wine blog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/992bf2cfb2f82fc24ac9112d53253af7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kingsman: The Golden Circle&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Golden Circle | 20th Century Fox&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry wine lovers, but while recently watching &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2802144&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Kingsman: Secret Service&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I got so irritated I felt import need to write about martinis. The reason being that, once again, Hollywood had maligned one of my favorite cocktails. In this episode, the character Galahad gives martini mixology instructions that finishes with “…Stirred for 10 seconds while glancing at an unopened bottle of vermouth.” Ugh! For the record, a martini without vermouth is actually ordered as; gin, straight, up, with olives. It is NOT a martini. More on this later. &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4649466&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Kingsman: Golden Circle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has the younger Galahad ordering a martini in a rustic Kentucky bar only to get a whiskey. The bartender answers, “In these parts that’s a martini.” Seriously? I’m pretty sure a state that invented the Mint Julep can properly mix a martini. That’s just Kingsman. Don’t even get me started on Bond films. Don’t get me wrong, I am a Bond fanatic, however his taste in martinis is appalling. First off, no proper Englishman would ever order a vodka…anything. Russians drink vodka. English drink gin. The damn stories are literally about cold war espionage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Daniel-Craig-007-martini.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vesper Cocktail&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Daniel Craig drinkin a Vodka Martini in Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come on! At least Ian Fleming’s concoction of gin, vodka, and Lillet was named something else (Vesper), which Daniel Craig creatively tried to rectify in &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0381061/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In other books and movies Bond vascillates, but ultimately seems to prefer vodka. More importantly, never for any reason, should a martini be shaken. We are not making a Ramos Fizz. A martini should be served beautifully clear and ice cold. No, Hollywood has not been kind to the Martini. So please, let’s take a moment to give it its due.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of the martini is a bit muddled. Not surprising, with literally just 2 ingredients just about anybody could have stumbled on to it. &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martini_(cocktail)&quot;&gt;Wikipedia says it is probably the drier cousin of the Martinez&lt;/a&gt;, which originated in San Francisco in the 1860s and was named after a little town across the Bay. However, there are many disputes to this claim. The real popularity of the Martini didn’t occur until the swinging 50s and 60s when young boomers were eschewing their parent’s brown liquor for the trendier gin and vodka drinks projected by Hollywood. While it would take decades for Whiskey to recover, the Martini never really lost its status. There are, like any cocktail, many variations. However, when referred to as one word “Martini” we are generally discussing the Dry Martini.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-martini&quot;&gt;My Martini&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/my_martini.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My Martini&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Martini. Stirred, not shaken.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with my own experience with the Martini. My family is divided by “Scotch/Irish” on my mother’s side and English on my father’s. The Scotch/Irish preferred beer and brown liquor. The English would drink just about anything – just as long as it was a martini. I remember my grandfather used to make up a “batch” in what appeared to be a lemonade pitcher that came with its own glass stir stick. He used &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.totalwine.com/spirits/gin/fleischmanns-gin/p/550750&quot;&gt;Fleischhman’s gin&lt;/a&gt; and whatever vermouth was on sale. Add ice, stir, and serve. His martinis were always served up with olives or pickled onions. I was once allowed a sip in my youth. A negative experience that left its mark on me until I was well into adulthood – by design, I’m sure. After which, I eventually learned to appreciate the tradition, dignity, and elegance that is…the Martini. My preferred martini is 2.5 parts Junipero gin, 1 part Dolin dry vermouth, stirred, served up with 2-3 medium/small pimento stuffed green olives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vodka-or-gin&quot;&gt;Vodka or Gin?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gin. However, since there is no other cocktail made of vodka and vermouth, Vodka Martinis are allowed. Just be certain you order it as such. Don’t try to get away with “Martini please, with vodka”. If I were mixing you would get a gin martini with a vodka splash. While I understand that some are put off by the taste and smell of juniper berries, I suggest you try different botanical gins until you find one that works. Ian Fleming’s literary James Bond ordered martinis that were half vodka, half gin. Perhaps start there and thumb your nose at the common Bond movie wannabe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-the-rocks&quot;&gt;On the Rocks?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted. Martinis are potent by design and should remain cold to the last sip. If ice helps get you there, so be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dirty&quot;&gt;Dirty?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted. The briny flavor from a splash of olive juice can hide the imperfections of mediocre gin and/or vermouth. However, if you have access to top notch gin, let it shine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chocolate-martini-etc&quot;&gt;Chocolate Martini, etc..&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/chocolate-martini-recipe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chocolate Martini...Not a Martini!&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not a Martini!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not permitted. These are, IMHO, abominations. In fact, I refer to them as “Abomitinis”. They are really Cosmos in disguise. With the exceptions for the “Vodka”, “Wet”, “Dry”, or “Perfect”, any cocktail who’s name ends with “Martini” is definitely NOT a martini. The trend started with the Appletini, which is permitted since it does not use the actual word “Martini”. The glass does not define the cocktail. If for some ungodly reason, you decided to pour a daiquiri into a martini glass would you call it a Daiquiri Martini? No, you would not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spray-rinse-or-hold-the-vermouth&quot;&gt;Spray, Rinse, or Hold the Vermouth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not permitted. While I understand the allure of good gin, vermouth is part of the cocktail. The original recipe was 2 parts gin to 1 part vermouth – which I still do in cases where the vermouth outshines the gin. Most of the time omitting vermouth happens because one has had a bad experience with off (vermouth does eventually go stale like any wine) or mediocre vermouth. Many bars unfortunately don’t always stock good vermouth or do not check their freshness. In these cases, by all means order a gin straight, but don’t call it a martini. On a side note, I commonly see this with Bombay Sapphire lovers. Personally, I’ve come to the conclusion that Sapphire does not pair well with vermouth, but is delicious straight and makes an excellent gin and tonic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“One martini is all right. Two are too many, 
and three are not enough”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;size-matters&quot;&gt;Size Matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt; cartoonist &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_ThurberCartoonist&quot;&gt;James Thurber&lt;/a&gt; once said, “One martini is all right. Two are too many, and three are not enough”. Alluding to how their potency can send one over the edge. However, my grandmother reversed the phrase one evening after inexplicably walking off a perfectly sound pier into a lake. After which she declared, “two are not enough and three are definitely too many”. It’s important to keep in mind that my grandmother drank martinis out of 4oz glasses. Served in this volume, two cocktails are not unreasonable. However, today it is common to find high-end bars serving $20 martinis in glasses that appear to have the volume of upside-down highway cones. There are two problems with this; One drink now becomes too many…and perhaps more importantly, sipped in moderation the liquid eventually begins to warm. There is nothing more off-putting than drinking a warm martini…and wasting $20 to boot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;garnish&quot;&gt;Garnish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as it doesn’t inhibit the flavor of the martini, just about any garnish is acceptable: stuffed olives, pickled onions, lemon twist, whatever suits your fancy. If for no other reason, to give the mixologist some creative outlet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;experimentation&quot;&gt;Experimentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contain yourself. There are many other cocktails for you to play with. Leave this classic alone. That being said, a drop of orange bitters or splash of Creme de Violet is mostly harmless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;know-your-gin&quot;&gt;Know Your Gin!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gin has a torrid history. Ostensibly, it was invented by the Dutch in the Middle Ages for medicinal purposes (some of us still use it in this way). However, gin became a plague in England during the early 1700s in a period known as the “Gin Craze”. Unable to grow good barley for beer, the English switched to gin with devastating results – addicting and killing people in epidemic proportions. “Bathtub Gin” entered our vocabulary in the US during prohibition. It literally refers to the practice of distilling spirits in one’s own bathtub. The results of which ran from dangerous to downright poisonous. By definition, gin is made from a neutral distilled spirit (aka vodka) that is infused with various “botanicals”. These typically include, but are not limited to, juniper berries, coriander, herbs, dried lemon or orange peel, etc.. The original Dutch version was rendered off-dry by whatever was infused post distillation. However, once the English got a handle on things they decided on a drier style that infused the botanicals during distillation, calling it “London Dry”. Martinis should be made with London Dry Gin. Cocktails made with other types of infused spirits, sloe gins, barrel-aged gins, etc.., again, should not to be called martinis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a some of my favorites in the affordable easy-to-find category:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Junipero&lt;/strong&gt;. Originally from the Maytag family of San Francisco Anchor brewing fame, this is a classic gin heavy-handed in juniper berries. It’s deliciously spicy, plays well with vermouth, and is not afraid of getting a little dirty. BE CAREFUL! This gin weighs in at 98.6 proof. Pour wisely.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hendricks&lt;/strong&gt;. Made in Scotland and uniquely infused with dried cucumber peel, this gin makes a clean, almost minty, martini. Those put off by juniper may want to start here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;St. Georges Botanical&lt;/strong&gt;. Another classic dry gin made near my home in Sonoma County, CA. It is akin to Junipero, but more subtle and slightly more complex. I am a bit lesser-handed with the vermouth here to let the gin shine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;St. Georges Terroir&lt;/strong&gt;. A less traditional spin made with California-based botanicals. This gin has some unique earthy citrus qualities that may be more attractive to vodka drinkers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tanqueray London Dry&lt;/strong&gt;. Classic, ubiquitous, affordable, …and potent. A heavy hitter at 94 proof, but a bit less balanced than Junipero. Tanqueray is my go-to for tall gin-and-tonics, but in a martini I tend to be heavy-handed with the vermouth and may even go extra dirty to soften its edge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bombay London Dry&lt;/strong&gt;. Sapphire’s lowly cousin, this is my baseline martini gin. Price points below this are generally unacceptable. It is traditionally juniper forward, subtle, well balanced, and inoffensive. If you love the flavor of good vermouth, this gin will not stand in its way. Perfect for the budget-minded martini drinker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-forget-the-vermouth&quot;&gt;Don’t Forget the Vermouth!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The martini’s brown liquor cousin, the Manhattan is much the same concept; booze and vermouth. Manhattan aficionados croon about the sweet vermouth they use and how it makes the drink. No one would ever attempt to make a manhattan without vermouth because that’s what Old Fashions are for. Inexplicably, martini lovers are less picky and have less options to choose from. However, I advise it be taken seriously. Like the Manhattan, vermouth can make or break a martini. Dry vermouth not only softens the spicy blow of the gin, but also adds floral and fruity character to the drink. It adds the necessary elegance and sophistication that is the Martini.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my suggestions. Quality dry vermouths are pretty reasonable, so don’t be a cheapskate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dolin Dry Vermouth&lt;/strong&gt;: Classic, floral, subtle, and not too citrusy. This is my workhorse that pairs well with just about any gin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carpano Bianco&lt;/strong&gt;: A little more forward than Dolin with more citrus. Works well with Junipero and Tanquery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noilly Prat Extra Dry&lt;/strong&gt;: Bracingly dry with herbal tea notes. This vermouth will spruce up Bombay martinis, as well as make dry up Hendricks ones. For something completely different, mix with St. Georges Terroir.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Martini is definitely an acquired taste. However, unlike Manhattans, quality ingredients are relatively affordable. It does not require a well-stocked bar. Nor does its maker have to be an accomplished mixologist. And, despite its simplicity, the Martini lover can sip with an air of sophistication not available to beer or margarita drinkers. Respectfully, the Martini.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 05:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/respectfully-the-martini/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/respectfully-the-martini/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tale of Two Counties. Napa vs. Sonoma. Part 9.</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-class-of-1972-and-the-paris-tasting-of-1976&quot;&gt;The Class of 1972 and The Paris Tasting of 1976&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/tale-of-two-counties-p8/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I discussed how the wine entrepreneurs of the 50’s and 60’s held the torch for others to produce quality wine in California. All we need now is a match. In this post we’ll find how a federal food bill, a bank investor report, and a little tasting in Paris helped launch California on to the world wine scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ap_6704110276.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robert F. Kennedy&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert F. Kennedy, April 2 1968&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;let-them-eat-grapes&quot;&gt;Let Them Eat Grapes!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert F. Kennedy was late to the presidential race of 1968, but quickly became a front-runner. His liberal platform was aimed at helping poor and disenfranchised Americans. One thing that astonished him was the amount of hunger in America. The 60’s were one of the most prosperous periods in American history, yet people were starving. The problem rested on simple economics of the time. Most Americans were thriving. Unemployment was low and wage growth was high. One of the fallouts of our success was the slow rise of inflation…which would eventually bite us in the next decade. Farming during this time wasn’t nearly as subsidized as it is today. Crops were more subject to fluctuations of the free market. Farming was also being hit by a year-over-year reduction in farmers. It would seem rising prosperity was inspiring farmer’s offspring to leave their fathers’ hard-scrabble lifestyle. Thus, the rise of inflation along with the reduction of supply was pressuring crop prices sharply upward. Americans experiencing wage inflation could afford the increase, but RFK brought to light America’s working poor who could not afford to feed their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFK’s tragic assassination in June of 1968 ended his run for the Presidency and Richard Nixon would become the victor. Nixon did not appear to have as much interest in helping the poor, but the hunger issue was not lost on him. He and his administration viewed it more of a security issue. America was already in a state of turmoil from Vietnam and civil rights protests. Many cities were in chaos, with the most recent confrontation at the Chicago Democratic Convention still fresh in everyone’s minds. Add mass starvation to the mix and you’ve got a civil nightmare. However, instead of following RFK’s edict of raising the poor’s standard of living, the Nixon administration chose to lower the price of food. During the first 2 years of his presidency America would see broad sweeping farm bills designed to subsidize crops, increase yields, and incentivize farming as a business. You know, farming–like corn, soybeans, wheat, and…grapes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/MNDVI_IconicFront-SP18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robert Mondavi Winery&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert Mondavi Winery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theres-something-happening-here&quot;&gt;There’s Something Happening Here&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, back in Napa. In 1966, with much fanfare, Robert Mondavi opened the first winery in California since prohibition. His tasting room was an architectural marvel. The winery was state-of-the-art and most the vineyards surrounding it belonged to Robert and his investors. Despite relative early success, this venture required borrowing money…a lot of money. In fact, borrowing money was something Robert would famously do until his death. In that way one could say Robert Mondavi was to wineries what Donald Trump is to hotels. However, unlike hotels, at this time the wine-making business was just another farming business. From a bank’s perspective, not a high-flying investment. Luckily, at least one bank saw things differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/0001_Wine-Grape-Dealers-Check.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bank of Italy Check&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bank of America was associated with the California wine business early on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day after the earthquake of 1906, Amadeo Giannini set up a make-shift table outside the rubble that was his office and began handing out loans to anyone who had a business and needed money to rebuild with nothing more than a written note and a handshake. His Bank of Italy would eventually be renamed the Bank of America, but its primary investments would stay in California for some time. BofA would compete against “gold” standard Wells Fargo for new investment opportunities in California’s rapidly growing economy. Even before prohibition BofA had investments in wine. In 1938 BofA created a marketing advisory board directed at fostering the California wine business. In 1967 it helped Gallo finance massive replanting of vines amongst its contracting vineyards. Then, in 1972 BofA put out its annual investor newsletter. This investor letter was like any other year, except this year the focus was on, yep, investing in California’s wine business. Success stories like Mondavi’s was proof there was money to be made in the wine business. The climate is right, the land is cheap, wine demand is up…but wait, isn’t this just farming? After all, this was an investor’s newsletter. What would an investor want with a grape farm? Well, since the aforementioned farm bills were passed, borrowing money to buy farm land was cheap and easy. In addition, owning a farm now comes with an annual agricultural tax deduction…and nothing makes a wealthy investor drool more than those two words. Plus, unlike other crops, growing grapes to make wine is a vertical business–in that you get to sell the finished product. Suddenly, owning a grape farm is also an investment opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note this was an “investor” newsletter. They were the target audience–not farmers or “wanna be” entrepreneurs. Few others had the resources to simply read an article and say, “I like California, what the Hell? Let’s go for it!” For most of us it could take a year or more of planning and saving in order to make such a move. The impact was only amplified that same year when the Wall Street Journal released a similar article confirming BofA’s summary. The wine biz investor class of 1972 was officially in session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not since the actual gold rush had California seen such a land grab. Below is a list of some of the notable wineries that opened for business in 1972.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chateau Montelena&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stag’s Leap Wine Cellars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diamond Creek Vineyards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caymus Vineyards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Burgess Cellars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carneros Creek Winery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chateau Chevalier&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clos Du Val&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dry Creek Vineyard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Edmeades Winery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jordan Vineyard &amp;amp; Winery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hacienda Cellars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mount Eden Vineyards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mount Veeder Winery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Silver Oak Cellars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stags’ Leap Winery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these brands, their founders, and their wines are now household names. Many of them were inspired by the articles from BofA and WSJ. Note that all but 4 are in Napa. However, 2 in particular stand out amongst the rest. Because in 1976 a little known event way off in Paris would permanently put them, and Napa, on the world’s wine map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/StevenSpurrier_780_old_fitbox_1000x600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steve Spurrier&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steve Spurrier. Courtesy of &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.oregonwinepress.com/&quot;&gt;Oregon Wine Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meanwhile-back-in-france&quot;&gt;Meanwhile, Back in France&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July of 1976 British expat cum Paris wine shop owner Steve Spurrier decided to showcase America’s effort in producing quality wines in honor of its 200th celebration of independence. He organized and hosted a wine tasting of cabernets and chardonnays from Napa, Bordeaux, and Burgundy. He invited a veritable who’s who of notable French wine experts to participate and rate the wines. And, just for fun, the tasting would be blind. What happened that day was completely unexpected…even by Spurrier himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the tasting commenced there were only a handful of attendees who knew which wines were which. Among them was a young Time magazine reporter named George M. Taber, who was there more for curiosity than a story. In his now famous book &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Judgment-Paris-George-M-Taber/dp/0743297326/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2E2DK1938ZEVG&amp;amp;keywords=judgement+of+paris+george+taber&amp;amp;qid=1579729663&amp;amp;sprefix=judgement+of+par%2Caps%2C202&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Judgement of Paris. California vs. France 1976&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; he tells a story of congeniality turned confusion, turned panic. Because as the tasting went on it became clear to everyone, the experts were having trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to interject an anecdote at this point in hopes of giving you an idea of what was happening. Some time ago I hosted a double-blind tasting of 10 sparkling wines (don’t try this at home, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com/how&quot;&gt;keep your tastings to 6 wines&lt;/a&gt;). It’s always fun to add a little challenge, so I selected a non-alcoholic brand to mix things up. We all tasted in progression (1-10). By the time we reached #6 some were starting to wonder, “did I miss the non-alcoholic one?” Each wine from then on only turned up the pressure. By the time we poured #10 we were all certain we had failed–that is until we tasted it. Despite being 9 wines deep in our cups, we instantly knew this was it and all had a hardy laugh of relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/winecollage_1024.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steve Spurrier&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paris Tasting of 1976 winners. Courtesy of &lt;a target=&quot;\_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/&quot;&gt;Smithsonian Magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in Paris, things were far more concerning. The idea of admitting that American wines were on par with that of the French, for these distinguished guests, could be career ending. Taber recalls at one point a taster stood up with a glass of chardonnay and proclaimed, “At last, French!”. Too which another taster muttered, “nonsense!” At that moment everyone knew…they were lost. In the end, 2 plucky upstarts from Napa won 1st place in both categories; Château Montelena for chardonnay, and Stag’s Leap Wine Cellars for cabernet sauvignon. The world was changed forever…or was it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, initially the world took little notice. In France the event was panned as illegitimate and shrugged off–although, reputations did suffer. In the US, Taber’s four-paragraph story was buried deep in that month’s edition of Time. Excitement stirred only amongst those in the know. However, things slowly started to change when oenophiles started calling boutique wine shops (many specializing in European wine) requesting California wines. Not just Montelena and Stag’s Leap (which quickly ran out of stock), but Mondavi, BV, and others. Many of these shop owners still had no idea about the tasting, but quickly began adding more US stock to meet demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived in CA as a teenager in 1977. My father and his friends frequented a local wine shop called Gene’s Country Liquors in Los Gatos where they occasionally held Euro vs. US tastings in a back room. It wasn’t long before these wine cronies were frequently making the 1 hour jaunts north to Napa and eventually, as I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p1/&quot;&gt;my post about wine clubs&lt;/a&gt;, joined a local winery’s wine club. By the late 70’s, the word was definitely out. CA made world class wine and Napa, now according to the French, made the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are (finally) near the end of my series on Napa vs. Sonoma. By now, it should be pretty obvious that by the late ’70s’ Napa has firmly established itself as a worldwide contender over-and-above other US wine regions, including Sonoma. Still, fortunes could change. There’s plenty of room for other regions to capture the limelight in the decades to come…but they didn’t. To this day Napa holds sway over other regions in regards to its prestige. In my next post I’ll discuss what, in the minds of wine lovers and experts, it is that puts Napa on its pedestal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 04:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/tale-of-two-counties-p9/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/tale-of-two-counties-p9/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tale of Two Counties. Napa vs. Sonoma. Part 8.</title>
        <description>&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/the-magnificent-seven-1200-1200-675-675-crop-000000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Magnificent 7&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-magnificent-7&quot;&gt;The Magnificent 7&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/tale-of-two-counties-p7/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I discussed the rise of the Gallo wine empire and its significance in re-introducing wine to Americans post prohibition. However, Gallo and its competitors were predominately in the low cost “jug” wine business. The few consumers seeking higher quality were mainly located in the metropolitan east coast and were buying well established European brands. Still, as early as the 1950s a handful of individuals in California were experimenting with French varietals in the quest to make wines of a quality that matched their Euro-rivals. I will focus this post on 7 individuals in particular that set early ground on the state–and indeed world’s–wine renaissance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/171112-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;André Tchelistcheff&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;André Tchelistcheff (1901-1994)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;andré-tchelistcheff&quot;&gt;André Tchelistcheff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A discussion of Napa wine history without mentioning the “Maestro” would be equivalent to reciting French history without Napoleon Bonaparte. In Napa his name is as famous as it is difficult to pronounce. Just as it was in the wine boom of the 1850s and 60s, the success of the Californian wine industry would depend on the education and experience brought by immigrants. Arguably, one of the earliest post prohibition premium wine producers in Napa was Beaulieu Vineyards (BV). Established before prohibition, founder Georges de Latour dedicated himself to producing wines that would rival those from his French homeland. Shortly after the repeal, de Latour traveled to France in search of an educated winemaker. The Russian born Tchelistcheff was already being courted by owners worldwide, but de Latour gave him an offer he couldn’t refuse as vice president and chief winemaker at BV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;God made Cabernet Sauvignon, whereas the Devil made Pinot Noir. - André Tchelistcheff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon his arrival in 1938, Tchelistcheff put an immediate focus on Cabernet Sauvignon paying particular attention to nuances of the grape’s development in the relatively warm, dry climate of Napa Valley. However, his real contributions to the California wine industry didn’t start until after Latour’s death in the 1950’s. Georges’ widowed wife Fernande proved less interested in making wine than making money and stifled many of Tchelistcheff’s efforts to improve quality. Frustrated, André began assisting other winemakers in the valley including Mike Grgich, Joe Heitz, and Robert Mondavi. After retiring from BV in 1973 he became a consulting enologist for Jordan Vineyard and ran his own private wine lab offering advice extending out to new up-and-coming regions in Oregon and Washington. André’s contributions and accolades are too many to list, but here are some notables:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noted the advantages of cold fermentation as it relates to the acidity and fruitiness of a wine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first winemaker to use American oak.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helped develop ways to control malolactic fermentation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Studying, developing many US wine regions including Carneros, Willamette Valley, and Columbia Valley.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognized by Wine Spectator in 2000 as “The Person Who Has Done the Most to Advance Wine Quality.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lee-stewart&quot;&gt;Lee Stewart&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J. Leland Stewart never like the pretense of having lineage to the Lelands of Stanford University fame, which is why he went simply by the name “Lee”. In 1943 he bought thirty acres of land on Napa’s Howell mountain for the purpose of agriculture. However unlike his prune-producing neighbors, Lee’s desire was to plant vines and start a winery that he would name Chateau Souverain (a play on the French “sovereign”). Without the benefit of any experience or education in viticulture or enology Lee relied predominately on observations and experimentation–with a sharp focus on consistency. In the lore of Napa wine personalities Lee Stewart is arguably the least known, but I find him an integral part in what were the earliest days of modern wine history. As other aspiring–and often clueless–wine makers arrived in Napa in the 1960s, they could look to Lee as one of the few able to offer them advice. His willingness to do so, along with André Tchelistcheff, Louis Martini, and Robert Mondavi fostered a trend of collaboration over the years to come that would be a key to Napa’s success vs. other regions. Lee’s biggest claim to fame was his hiring of Mike Grgich, immigrating him to the US, and thus launching the career of what would be another Napa legend. However, he deserves many other lesser known accolades:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduced and named varietal Petit Sirah (later recognized as French varietal Duriff).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early advocate of “clean wine making practices” introducing hygienic practices that would only be adopted around the world decades later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Championed Martin Ray’s philosophy of single-varietal winemaking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outspoken proponent of practicing the French standard of fermenting Chardonnay &lt;em&gt;sur-lee&lt;/em&gt; in oak barrels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 1963 Chateau Souverain would win 93 medals at the California State Fair. Then the standard for judging quality California wine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/0fed4221e9b0b6f9475a02c6cb3f3c56-articleLead.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Miljenko “Mike” Grgich&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miljenko “Mike” Grgich. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palmspringslife.com&quot;&gt;– © Palm Springs Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mike-grgich&quot;&gt;Mike Grgich&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well known as an irascible curmudgeon from Croatia, the name Mike Grgich (Miljenko Grgić) seems to be at the center of any major conversation in the wine industry throughout the second half of the 20th century. Like his mentor Tchelistcheff, his route to the US was circuitous coming from war-ravaged and communist Eastern Europe. First hired by Lee Stewart at Chateau Souverain, Grgich went on to work for Tchelistcheff at BV, then Chateau Montelena, Christian Brothers, and Robert Mondavi before partnering with Austin Hills (Hills Brothers Coffee) to start his own winery Grgich Hills. In the 80’s and 90’s Grgich was recognized as one of the “big 3” Chardonnay producers along with Far Niente and ZD Wines. Together they set the standard for a style of richness that set Napa apart. Recently, Grgich’s contribution to the famous Chardonnay that won the Paris Wine Tasting of 1976 was omitted by the movie &lt;em&gt;Bottle Shock&lt;/em&gt;. The movie falsely portrayed owner/partner Pat Barret as the winemaker. Although, initially consulted by the movie’s producers, rumor has it Grgich’s famously abrasive behavior got him written out of the script. Of the 5 people I mention in this post Grgich is the soul survivor at 95 and is easily recognizable wearing his signature beret. Like Tchelistcheff, Grgich’s accolades are overwhelming, but here’s just a few:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Winemaker of the winning Chardonnay in the famous Paris Wine Tasting of 1976.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His first vintage at Grgich Hills won the 1980 Chardonnay Showdown over 221 entries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inducted into the Culinary Institute’s Vintner’s Hall of Fame&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Beard Award winner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;louis-p-martini&quot;&gt;Louis P. Martini&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his youth the shy, introverted Louis P. Martini stood in the shadow of his gregarious bigger than life father Louis M. Martini. Louis M. followed the same risks and path of Cesare Mondavi during prohibition by getting out of the grape business and into winemaking. Louis M. always believed prohibition was an aberration and so started his winery in 1922. Son Louis P. took over in 1946 and set about focussing on making high quality wine. Luckily, his father had purchased some choice acreage around Napa and bordering Sonoma to work with, including Monte Rosso on the back side of Mt. Veeder which, IMHO produces some of the best Cabernets. Starting in 1962 Louis P. ventured further a field east to Chiles Valley and Carneros in the south. Carneros, in particular, was frowned upon as a wine region at the time. However, around 1973 Louis P. started to recognize the success of Pinot Noir in his Carneros vineyards. At that time Pinot was commonly grown along with Zinfandel and Cabernet in the hotter Napa Valley. Then, California Pinot was gritty and heavy in body like any other red. Martini was one of the first to recognize it’s elegance when grown in cooler climates like the foggy bay-hugging Carneros district. Today, Carneros is the only region where Napa County still grows Pinot Noir. Both father and son were active in their small Napa wine community. Louis M. helped found the Napa Valley Vintners Assoc. Louis P. served on the Wine Advisory Board. Both were advocates for collaboration in the valley. Here are some of Louis P.’s accomplishments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to plant grapes in Carneros.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to produce a vintage Merlot in California.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early advocate and grower in the Sonoma’s Russian River Valley.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early proponent of mountain vineyards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inducted into the Culinary Institute’s Vintner’s Hall of Fame.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG-cr-sm-1919x799.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jack and Jamie Davies&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jack and Jamie Davies. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.schramsberg.com&quot;&gt;– © Schramsberg Vineyards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jack-davies&quot;&gt;Jack Davies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s not surprising that a high society couple out of Beverly Hills might have a taste for Champagne, it’s arguable whether they would have the grit and wear-with-all to actually make it. Jack and Jamie Davies were partners and I am being remiss—if not sexist—for omitting Jamie’s name from the header, but this is a post about individuals and Jack was the winemaker. The Davies were bit by the “back to nature” bug and in 1965 bought an old ghost winery once owned by a German immigrant named Jacob Schram back in the late 1800’s. Unlike most old wineries, this one was unique in that Schram had hewed a cave into the Diamond Mountain hillside property. This suited Jack as he was not here to make still wines like most of his neighbors. The Davies were interested in making sparkling wine that rivaled vintage Champagne. This meant growing the same grapes, adhering to Champagne’s &lt;em&gt;Methode Traditionale&lt;/em&gt; winemaking process, and riddling/aging wine in caves. Despite his ambitions, Jack was not an accomplished winemaker. Luckily, neighbors like Louis Martini, André Tchelistcheff, and the Mondavi brothers were so enamored with the idea of world class sparkling being made in Napa Valley they chipped in to help Jack figure it out. Initially word was slow, but steady, producing 1,000 cases by 1970. Fortunes changed in 1972 when California native Richard Nixon carried 25 cases to China to celebrate the return of diplomatic relations there. An act that has made Schramsberg a mainstay in the White House cellar to this day. The next California president, Ronald Reagan, was known to serve it to congressional easterners and jokingly challenge them to find a better wine in France. The Davies’ success story of making quality sparkling wine in California eventually got out to Europe which sparked a buying spree of Carneros land by famous French cellars like Tattinger, Moet &amp;amp; Chandon, Mumm, and Spanish Cava producer Cordoníu. The Davies were not the first to make sparkling wine in California…they just set the standard. They were also active in other fronts regarding Napa Valley. Here are some of their accomplishments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to plant Champagne varietals/clones in Napa.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to produce sparkling wine in California using Champagne’s traditional method.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First to produce vintage Blanc de Noirs (1967)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leaders in the movement to declare Napa Valley an agricultural perserve.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Successfully helped stop the widening of highway 29 from 2-to-4 lanes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schramsberg has been served at White House events by every President since 1972.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Robert-Mondavi-10004083.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Robert Mondavi&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert Mondavi. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbrands.com/&quot;&gt;– © Constellation Brands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;robert-mondavi&quot;&gt;Robert Mondavi&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 7 mentioned here, none are arguably more famous than Robert Mondavi…and Robert wouldn’t have it any other way. Mondavi was an excellent winemaker in his own right, but his real skills and contribution to the wine industry were in marketing. While everyone else was in the pursuit of creating high quality wine, Robert was obsessed with how sell it to the masses. Even though Robert’s contributions to the wine industry really didn’t erupt until the 1970s I include him in this list because it was his early marketing vision in the 1960s that helped future wineries find consumers beyond their tasting rooms. Mondavi is the father of a vision that fine wine should be a part of everyday American life. Elevating people to aspire beyond the jug. To say Robert was restless would be an understatement. Born in Lodi, CA Robert and his brother Peter helped their grape-growing father Cesare start a new venture after buying Charles Krug Winery in St. Helena. By 1946 CK Mondavi had established a reputation for producing affordable everyday wines. However, after their father’s death in 1959 the brothers grew contentious. While Peter believed in his father’s vision Robert had higher aspirations. By 1965 their infamous feud had exploded with Robert leaving the winery in a controversial manor to start his own Robert Mondavi Winery. Robert immediately started spending and borrowing to fund his ambitions. A practice that kept him in debt the rest of his life. However, no expenses were spared. Robert always purchased the best equipment and his modern winery and tasting room built in 1966 began an opulent Vegas-like building boom that continues today. The same attention was spent on his wine in consulting Andre Tchelistcheff and ultimately hiring Mike Grgich. However, Robert’s ambitions would eventually get the best of him resulting in an embarrassing sale of his winery and name to Constellation Brands. even still, his legacy is revered and his accomplishments are many. Here are but a few:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revived the unpopular Sauvignon Blanc by aging it in oak and selling it under the name “Fumé Blanc.” A practice so successful many other winemakers across the state followed suit and the made up nomer continues to this day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stopped the decline of the maligned Zinfandel by introducing it to French oak and selling on par with the more popular Cabernet Sauvignon. Although, Napa vintners continued to replace their Zin with Cab, Sonoma vintners followed Robert’s example and kept Zin as their cult favorite.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By establishing his Woodbridge brand with a large production facility in Lodi, Mondavi brought 750ml premium Napa wine to the masses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partnered with Baron Philippe de Rothschild of Chateau Mouton Rothschild fame to found Opus One–which quickly became one of the Napa’s first cult Cabernets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contributed millions of dollars to UC Davis’ enology and viticulture programs helping feed the growing demand for educated winemaking and vineyard staff throughout the US.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Martin-Ray-pours-wine-namesake-Saratoga-winery.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Martin Ray&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Martin Ray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;martin-ray&quot;&gt;Martin Ray&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a series about Napa vs. Sonoma. This post is about early pioneers of the modern wine era. The first 6 mentioned operated in Napa Valley. This, the 7th and final, did not. Nor did he in Sonoma. Martin Ray hails from the region I first discovered wine and still hold very dear–the Santa Cruz Mountains. Martin Ray makes this list because way back in 1936, even before Lee Stewart, he was an outspoken advocate of single varietal wines and varietal labeling. At a time when bulk wine producers were producing wines like California Chablis and Hearty Burgundy (neither of which had much, if any, of their French namesake grapes), Ray was adamant that wines should be 100% varietal and labeled as such. Surprising, since his mentor was none other than Paul Masson, a successful bulk producer who ironically sold his vineyards to Ray. Eventually Ray’s vision caught on. Not just in the Santa Cruz Mountains, but all over California. Bombastic, boastful, eccentric, and perhaps a bit crazy, Ray was famous for lavish parties and outlandish statements. His wine was adored by critics, but expensive and hard to get. Ray’s antics eventually got him forced out of the business by his financial partners in 1972, but his vision on how wine should be produced and labeled actually became law in 1982. Although I have no professional accolades for Martin Ray, I shiver at the prospect of rows of bottles being labeled “California Red Wine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I chose 7 individuals who were pivotal in California’s movement to produce quality wine beyond the then current “jug” standard. Admittedly, my selection is subjective. However, one thing is fairly obvious…6 out of 7 operated in Napa Valley. Oh, Sonoma was producing quality wine in the early days, but with less vigor. In fact, heavily funded Hanzell Winery near downtown Sonoma had become a virtual experimentation lab frequented by some of the pioneers mentioned in this post. Still, there weren’t the personalities, collaboration, and vision that was going on in Napa at the time. The Delingers, DeLoach’s, Bynums, Strongs, Stares, would all come later. But at the end of the 1960’s, thanks to winemakers like my magnificent 7, the modern wine era had emerged. In my next post we will find out how a Federal farm bill, an ambitious winemaker, and an investment-seeking bank touched off a wave of new California vintners known as the Class of ‘72.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 05:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/tale-of-two-counties-p8/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/tale-of-two-counties-p8/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Tasting Beta Program.</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;yno-tasting-as-a-winery-event&quot;&gt;Yno Tasting as a Winery Event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yno concept evolved from the most asked question I received during my time in hospitality, “How do I find wines I like?” It made me think about my own wine journey and how important blind tasting wine in a comparative setting has helped me discover my own palate as well as enjoyment of wine. However, blind tastings should have rules and structure if there is going to be any benefit–a perfect challenge for an old wine guy with a programming problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yno Tasting is intended to be as much a consumer app as an industry event. The idea is for wine enthusiasts to set up Yno Tasting accounts in order to participate in public events hosted by wineries, wine bars, or even virtually by wine experts. With that experience they should be encouraged to host their own private events. Yno Tasters and Hosts will have an ongoing record of their tastings, ratings, and comments. Meanwhile the accumulation of all Yno Tasting events will provide valuable comparative data to the industry as a whole. It’s a win-win for both industry and consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;yno-tasting-beta-program&quot;&gt;Yno Tasting Beta Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all has to start some where. That is why I am introducing a beta program to help kickstart winery events. I believe once winery customers recognize how much fun blind tastings are, they will host their own tastings, wineries will get increased loyalty, cats and dogs living together, the possibilities are endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-host-a-public-yno-tasting-event&quot;&gt;How to Host a Public Yno Tasting Event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public events are conducted as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a Yno Tasting Host account on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;https://ynotasting.com&lt;/a&gt;. It is preferable to use the wine maker or owner’s name on the account to bring credibility to the event regardless of who actually hosts it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a Yno Tasting Event. Name the event appropriately with your establishment name as well as other pertinent info like new releases, library, vertical, etc… It is up to the host whether to reveal the wines being tasted, or keep it a surprise until tasting time. Keep in mind this is not intended to be a competition as much it is a discovery. For responsible hospitality reasons it is recommended to keep your list to just 6 wines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yno Tasting Invitations. It is recommended to use your normal event system to invite your guests, accept payment, etc… After a guest confirms attendance, use the Yno Tasting invite system to send them a confirmation and link to signing up as Yno Tasting Guest for your event. Yno Tasting Guest confirmations will be sent to the host’s email account. Non-confirmed guests can still sign up on arrival.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tasting Day!
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;IMPORTANT! Your guests will need to bring their cell phones and your facility will need reliable cell or wifi coverage in order to conduct the event. See beta hosting information below about using Amazon Alexa devices.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Until all wines are revealed, they are referred to by number. Use numbered bottles/carafes of the same shape and size. Best practice is to provide one glass per bottle with matching number for each guest. This will speed things along and require less pouring staff than using one glass per Guest.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expect the event to last about 1.5 hours for 6 wines. This should allow enough time for wine introductions and tasting instructions. It is recommended to set a “close” date/time for your event which will trigger a hard stop and block any further entry. At this point the host can reveal the wines via the app and the event is over.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post event data. All tasting data will remain available for review for each event under the Host’s account as well as to their Guests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beta-host&quot;&gt;Beta Host.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yno Tasting is currently in beta. During this period I strongly recommend using me as your host for at least your first tasting. This is to make sure everything goes smoothly and for me to observe what works and what needs improvement. I have over 3 years of experience in hospitality at &lt;a href=&quot;https://chateaustjean.com&quot;&gt;Chateau St. Jean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://drycreekvineyard.com&quot;&gt;Dry Creek Vineyard&lt;/a&gt; where I’ve conducted many hospitality events such as tours, tastings and blendings. I come with CSW and WSET III wine education certificates and references. In addition, I will bring Alexa devices which offer another fun dimension to your event. For the beta period I am charging a modest $50 fee to manage and host your event. Please keep in mind that I do have a day job at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wineglassmarketing.com&quot;&gt;WineGlass Marketing&lt;/a&gt; (which by-the-way is available to help promote your event) that limits my availability to nights and weekends. Should your event be a success–which I’m certain it will–you are welcome to host future events with your own staff. Currently, there is no cost to use the platform, however that is subject to change in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested parties can reach me at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Langley&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bill@ynoguy.com&quot;&gt;bill@ynoguy.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(o) 707-237-6904&lt;br /&gt;
(m) 408-314-4304&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 09:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/yno-tasting-event-beta-hosting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/yno-tasting-event-beta-hosting/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What the Hell is a Wine Club? Final Post.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my final post on my wine club series. In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p1/&quot;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; I illustrated the difference between retail and DTC clubs. In &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/&quot;&gt;post 2&lt;/a&gt; I illustrated the genesis of why wine clubs even exist. In this post I will hypothesize the future of wine clubs in the rapidly changing world of hand-crafted adult beverages and end this series with my 7 tips on choosing a wine club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;craft-beer-is-here&quot;&gt;Craft Beer is Here!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/maxresdefault.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Santa Rosa Brews&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where wine country meets beer city&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve mentioned before I live in Sonoma County. A county once best known as a premium wine producer. That was until 2 years ago when my home town of Santa Rosa was named &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sonomamag.com/santa-rosa-named-microbrew-capital-united-states/&quot;&gt;Microbrew Capital of the US&lt;/a&gt;.  My wife and I own a home downtown within a mile of the famed &lt;a href=&quot;https://russianriverbrewing.com&quot;&gt;Russian River Brewing&lt;/a&gt; Co. We have an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/21461228&quot;&gt;Airbnb&lt;/a&gt; which is often booked up 20+ days a month. You would think that is because I offer wine tours and advice to my guests, but you would be wrong. Nearly half of our guests are beer tourists and most are a blend of beer and wine, as well as cider and spirits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craft brewing has swept the nation. I visit Bend, OR every year where brew pubs outnumber coffee shops. In my birth town of Milwaukee, WI, once dominated by Miller Brewing, craft breweries are popping up everywhere. In fact, it is arguably hard to find a town in the US that doesn’t have one. People are excited to try each new limited release and pay upwards of $10/pint! Stand outside RRBC at 11a on Sunday morning you will see scores of beer tourists and locals walking out with their case of Pliny the Elder. Come back in February and you’ll see them lined up around the block for week to get their 2 pints of Pliny the Younger. It’s a phenomenon that has swept the nation. People have come to realize that small batch beer…well, tastes better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dt.common.streams.StreamServer.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Line at RRBC&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Published by the Press Democrat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-good-for-beer-is-good-for-wine-right&quot;&gt;What’s Good for Beer is Good for Wine, Right?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I discuss in my &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/tale-of-two-counties-p1/&quot;&gt;Tale of Two Counties series&lt;/a&gt;, quality small batch wine has been around here in California since before the 1960s. One would think recent rise in trends like craft breweries and farm-to-table food can only benefit the wine industry. Well, not quite. There is one glaring advantage why small batch beer, cider, spirits, and even food, have over wine…they can be made ANYWHERE. As I’ve said 1,000 times quality wine comes from vineyards and quality vineyards can’t thrive just anywhere. Plus, the faster you can get those grapes from vine to fermentation, the better your chances of a quality product. The same is not true of grains, hops, or apples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pubs-not-clubs&quot;&gt;Pubs Not Clubs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A beer made in Lincoln, Nebraska has the same potential quality as a beer made here in Santa Rosa. For that reason, microbrews focus solely their local market where they can depend on local brew pubs and restaurants for distribution. As breweries increase they are facing the same limited distribution issue as wine. The days of starting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://https://lagunitas.com&quot;&gt;Lagunitas Brewing Company&lt;/a&gt; story are fast closing, so new establishments don’t even try. Stay small, local, and thrive is the new model. Subsequently, new wineries are adopting the same model–which is great…if you live here. Not so much if you live in Lincoln. Although I’ve never been there, I’m reasonable certain I could find a good local brew. However, I am also certain I could not find a local wine of the same caliber as I can here in Santa Rosa. Sure, I would likely find a good quality small batch wine from CA, OR, WA, etc… in a local shop or restaurant, but as I discussed in my &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; over time that is likely to change. The wine industry is rapidly bifurcating into local small batch vs. mass produced distribution–with very little in between. It’s the same for beer, but with less consequences depending on where you live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-the-club-alive&quot;&gt;Keep the Club Alive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why winery wine clubs are so important. Unfortunately, many of wineries have turned their clubs into overly aggressive sales programs. For some wineries it’s out of greed, for others it’s a desperate act of survival. Don’t get me wrong, even the best wineries have to be clever in the face of competition, but there is a point of diminishing returns. As a club salesman, I have witnessed it first hand. Today I work as a software developer in wine marketing where I hope to help evolve the club system into something more friendly and accessible to consumers. My wish is some day we can eliminate the need for aggressive tasting room sales tactics. I believe if we don’t throttle this, eventually clubs will turn consumers away from wine rather than towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now I can at least recommend to wine lovers my 7 tips on how to pick a good wine club:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beware of the conglomerates:&lt;/strong&gt; I want to be clear not to steer you away from conglomerate owned wineries. There are honest business models out there where subsidiaries are producing quality small batch wines. Many allow you to enjoy your discounts at their sister wineries, which is a big benefit. Simply do your research before signing up. For instance, when the salesman tells you, “You can’t find this in any stores,” casually pull out your phone and look it up. It’s not that they’re lying to you, just more likely they don’t know what happens in the boardroom. Another easy trick is look for a barcode sku on the label. All distributed wines require one, while DTC wines do not. Never join a club where any of the wines may be distributed. You’re better off joining a club at your local wine shop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s their story?&lt;/strong&gt; The genesis of a winery tells a lot about what goes into making the product. There are lots of very small wineries with stories like, “John Doe made a ton of money as a hedge fund investor. He learned a lot about wine on his (multiple) trips to France. So, 3 years ago he and his wife thought, ‘Why not?’ and here we are. His wife now runs the winery. This bottle is named after his daughter.” At this point, I usually like to ask questions like, “Is his wife on the property right now?” “Do they make the wine?” “Do they live here full time?” I think you know what the answers are. These are what we call “lifestyle” vintners. To them, winemaking is a tax-deductible hobby…not a passion. Steer clear.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vineyard relationships:&lt;/strong&gt; Good wine starts with great vineyards. Great vineyards are hard to find and even harder to maintain. Wineries that establish long-term contracts with vineyards usually produce quality wines from them year-over-year. This is important if you plan to be a long-term member. Wineries that own vineyards are even better, because they have full control and generally have more cash to put towards winemaking. If a winery commonly produces wine from different vineyards every year, unless the winemaker really knows his craft, there is a likelihood consistency will suffer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ecology matters:&lt;/strong&gt; Wine is an agricultural product. It is essentially farming. Anyone who takes it seriously cares about the land and community it comes from. Vineyard sustainability, dry farming, climate change, watershed preservation, local wild life, community and farm worker support are all topics of conversation you should be hearing and having at the winery. Bad behavior is well documented. Know who the good guys are.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy wine, not trophies:&lt;/strong&gt; Wines costing over $100/bottle are basically like printing money. Despite all the accolades you might hear about them, there is nothing in the vineyard or cellar that can justify that price other than demand–and demand is usually driven by hype, not quality. Unless you are looking to impress the likes of Robert Parker with your wine cellar, focus on wines you can taste, afford, and enjoy every day. Besides, nobody likes a snob.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be wary of scarcity:&lt;/strong&gt; Small batch wines are by nature limited in quantity. However, there are wineries that take advantage of scarcity as a business model. There are famous examples called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/collectors-clamor-for-napas-cult-wines-51544882400&quot;&gt;cult wines&lt;/a&gt;, which are almost impossible to come by and often run in excess of $500/bottle. This can be an expensive and frustrating game to play where wines are often doled out in what’s called “allocation”. For every day wine drinkers the experience can sometimes feel indignant and humiliating. There are good allocation models where access is guaranteed with some benefits, but I consider these programs different than a traditional wine club. They are strictly about the wine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Membership should have privileges:&lt;/strong&gt; Most wine clubs come with benefits. Discounts should be at the top of the list, but many offer free or discounted events, tours, winemaker dinners, merchandise, etc.. For those of us who love the winery “experience” as much as the wine, these perks are important. As a member you are virtually a stock holder in their business. A good winery should always make you feel like a VIP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it! Hopefully, now you know what the hell a wine club is and whether it’s something you want to get into to. Feel free to reach out to me with questions and comments on this often controversial topic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 05:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-final/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-final/</guid>
        
        <category>wineclub</category>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Tasting</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;another-left-turn&quot;&gt;Another left turn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I announced some &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/up-dry-creek-with-a-pin/&quot;&gt;pretty big career changes&lt;/a&gt;. Back then I was starting my first full-time job in the wine industry and had aspirations of being a “high-end” wine educator and blogger. My software developer days were forever behind me–or so I thought. After about a year I started feeling uncomfortable in my role as an “educator.” I started getting imposter syndrome and, more importantly, I didn’t feel like I was  helping people discover wine for themselves. After all, I wanted to be an educator, not an expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also, as a software developer, finding myself increasingly frustrated with the sales and marketing software I was using in my job. So, after two years at Dry Creek Vineyard—an experience that I will always cherish—I decided to take a job with a small direct-to-consumer marketing company called &lt;a href=&quot;https://wineglassmarketing.com&quot;&gt;WineGlass Marketing&lt;/a&gt; as a data analyst and programmer. At the same time I enrolled in a software bootcamp to retool my development skills and while there decided to develop a software app idea I had been toying with for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Have you ever asked yourself why Sommeliers and Wine Masters have to take those arduous blind tasting tests? Sure, they have to show they can recognize what’s in the glass, but it’s also the best way to actually learn. Students do blind tastings to get good at them, but they also learn the different nuances of varietals, styles and regions along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love tasting wine blind—even though I’m not particularly good at it. I especially like to do it with friends. If you ever want to make a wine snob cringe, invite them to a blind tasting. It’s a lot of fun, but more importantly, it’s flat out the best way to discover wines you like with no flowery descriptions, no pretty labels, and no point scores. It’s just you and your senses comparing 6 wines. You either like it, or you don’t…and isn’t that all that matters?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-yno&quot;&gt;Let’s Yno!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/yno_tasting_logo_512.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yno Tasting&quot; class=&quot;portfolio-hero-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own blind tasting experiences my friends and I always struggled with doing the tally at the end of the tasting. Sure, we all knew what we liked, but what did everyone like? What was the best buy? This required math. Something nobody should have to deal with after a night of tasting wine. So, for many years the idea of a blind wine tasting app has been kicking around in my head. Done right, the app would have to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a hosted invite system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Display tasting and wine descriptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep track of taster scores and comments by wine number&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep a running tab on overall tasting statistics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close a tasting and reveal the wines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage interaction between tasters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Store tasting data for tasters to review later&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be fun and easy to use (this one especially)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;Yno Tasting&lt;/a&gt;. This app will hopefully accomplish what I originally set out to do as a wine educator: help people enjoy wine more by learning what they like. The app is free for all to use. Just sign up as a &lt;em&gt;Yno Host&lt;/em&gt; and start your own tasting. I will provide affordable suggested tasting lists of commonly found wines for those needing a kickstart. Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bill@ynoguy.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; with your questions/suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now get out there, and &lt;em&gt;Go Blind!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 02:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/yno-tasting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/yno-tasting/</guid>
        
        <category>wine software</category>
        
        
        <category>Software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What the Hell is a Wine Club? Part 2.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p1/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I tried to explain the definition of a wine club, and the difference between a retail wine club and a winery wine club. In this post I will try to explain the evolution of the wine club and why they exist in the first place. The fact of the matter is wine clubs are now basically loyalty programs, but that’s not how they started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-very-brief-history-of-alcohol-in-america&quot;&gt;A (Very) Brief History of Alcohol in America&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s 1933 and America’s great experiment, Prohibition, is failing miserably. Americans now disapprove of the 19th Amendment by an overwhelming majority. Organized crime has become more brazen and incredibly wealthy distributing illegal hooch from Canada, Europe, and the Caribbean. Moonshiners are showing off their get-away cars in a new sport called “stock car” racing. Citizens are poisoning themselves with “bath tub” gin and wineries are selling unusually high amounts of “sacramental” wine. The federal government has had enough. However, Prohibition was a part of the Constitution and, as we currently know with the ACA, turning it back won’t be easy. It will require another Amendment and many states are still quite satisfied with the status quo. Compromise will be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reticent states insisted they should be able to control the flow of alcohol across their borders. Legally, interstate trade is protected under the Constitution–but these were desperate times. The solution came to be known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parkstreet.com/wine-spirits-industry-background/&quot;&gt;3 Tier system&lt;/a&gt;. It declared that alcohol production, distribution, and retail were to be separated entities giving states full control over distribution. Retailers would not be allowed to purchase alcohol directly from a producer, making each state’s distributor a gatekeeper. It was a strange “tail wagging the dog” compromise that was hastily drafted for ratification, albeit wrought with loopholes and constitutional hypocrisy. Some states like Utah and Ohio chose to handle distribution as a government function. Other states restricted distributor licenses to just a handful. Subsequently, 80 years later the system &lt;a href=&quot;https://fermentationwineblog.com/2018/09/a-corrupt-scheme-at-the-middle-of-the-american-wine-industry/&quot;&gt;looks nothing like what was intended&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://winefolly.com/update/three-tier-system/&quot;&gt;is straining in the face of corporate deregulation and the internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-very-brief-history-of-wine-distribution-in-america&quot;&gt;A (Very) Brief History of Wine Distribution in America&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the end of Prohibition wine was largely made in bulk by brands like Gallo, Inglenook, and Almaden. With so few producers making relatively few large volume labels, it was easy for distributors to carry virtually every wine made. However, as early as the 1950’s small wineries in California like Robert Mondavi, Louis Martini, Beaulieu Vineyards, and others were producing small batch wines. Most of the country didn’t take notice until the famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judgment_of_Paris_(wine)&quot;&gt;Paris Tasting of 1976&lt;/a&gt; when California Cabernet and Chardonnay suddenly achieved world acclaim. Small wine producers started popping up everywhere–particularly in California, which to date has over 1,500 wine producers. On the other hand, while the number of wine producers was exploding, the number of state distributors were doing the exact opposite. One of the loopholes of the 3 Tier system permits distributors to operate in multiple states, thus enabling mergers and acquisitions. A once small Florida distributor called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/companies/southern-wine-spirits/#7787f1415a59&quot;&gt;Southern Wine &amp;amp; Spirits&lt;/a&gt; now controls the flow of alcohol in over 35 states. The result: thousands of wineries trying to get a relative handful of distributors to carry their products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 1rem&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/free-the-grapes-angry-grape-guy.png&quot; alt=&quot;freethegrapes.org&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;font-size: .75em&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Free the Grapes! (freethegrapes.org)! An organization dedicated to direct-to-consumer shipping causes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-dtc-shipping&quot;&gt;Introducing DTC Shipping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we have here is a failure to distribute which, when you think about it, is just another form of prohibition. And like in Prohibition, consumers and wine producers often became partners in crime. With a nod-and-wink wine would be shipped marked as “olive oil” or some other non-restricted product. Punishment for such crimes–especially for the winery-could be severe, including loss of their wholesale license. Effectively banning the sale of their wine to the entire state! However, wine producing states started to realize it was unreasonable and just bad business to not allow their own small wine producers the ability to sell direct-to-consumer (DTC) when the consumer had no other means to purchase the product. “Reciprocity” deals, as they were called, were drawn up between states that allowed the free flow of wine between producers and consumers of limited quantities. Eventually, other states started opening up some form of direct shipping as well. Even though wholesalers and distributors effectively sought legislation to strike down reciprocity, the proverbial cat is now out of the bag and over 40 states now allow some form of DTC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-inevitable-collision&quot;&gt;The Inevitable Collision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say the least, wholesalers and distributors don’t like direct sales. They view it as a loophole to what is their constitutional domain. They have fought it tooth-and-nail over the years through lobbyists, law suits, and political contributions. However, consumer demand, producer frustration, and the enforcement of interstate trade laws have been slowly chipping away at their stronghold. Given their situation you would think they’d try to be more accommodating to small producers. In fact, again, they are doing just the opposite. They are shunning them in favor of working more exclusively with wine conglomerates. Why? Well, they actually have mutually exclusive motivations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For conglomerates, forcing small producers to sell out increases their own portfolio. Having more brands gives them leverage over distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For distributors, dealing exclusively with conglomerates enables them to access larger portfolios with less leg work and more bargains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a win-win…except for consumers and retailers. In many instances, wine shops and restaurants are forced into purchasing big brand wine since most of them are at the mercy of what the distributor carries. Meanwhile in stores wine aisles are looking more like cereal aisles. Lots of pretty labels…from just a handful of corporations. So the battle rages on, but inch-by-inch DTC is gaining ground. Since I entered the wine biz 5 years ago formerly stalwart distribution states like Pennsylvania, Massachusetts, and now Oklahoma have opened up. Fundamentally, 3-Tier violates interstate trade commerce law and everyone knows it is just one Supreme Court decision away from being overturned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dtc--wine-club&quot;&gt;DTC = Wine Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah, back to wine clubs. Small batch wines are the least likely to be distributed for obvious reasons. They are also often the most highly rated available. Consumers clamor for these wines, but buying them takes timing. Many of these wines disappear weeks, or even days, after they’re released. Oh sure, you can get on an email list, but wouldn’t it just be better if you can have your favorite new releases automatically shipped to your door when they come out..guaranteed? This is why, as I alluded in the beginning of this series, I favor winery wine clubs over others. Retail clubs have to rely more on gimmicks to compete. I find some of their claims to be rather dubious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We search for hard-to-get wines.&lt;/strong&gt; As I said before, if they’re not coming directly from a winery, they are sold on the open market. Look it up in your &lt;a href=&quot;https://delectable.com&quot;&gt;Delectable&lt;/a&gt; app…you’ll probably find it. Besides, just because it’s hard to find doesn’t mean you’ll like it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our panel will select wines especially for you.&lt;/strong&gt; Really?! An “expert” selects wine for someone they don’t really know. This is literally the blind leading the blind. Why not just go to your local wine shop and ask them for advice? At least you can actually meet the expert.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’ll select wines based on your sample ratings.&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe you’ve seen this. They send you some sample vials of wine. You tell them which ones you liked and…Voila! Every wine after will be perfect. Like most, the first wine I ever tasted and liked was sweet and cheap. My taste has changed quite a bit since then…and continues to do so. Listen, if you really want to track what you like use my software &lt;a href=&quot;https://ynotasting.com&quot;&gt;YnoTasting&lt;/a&gt;. After all, it’s your palate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many retail clubs offer great wines and values, but the fact is only a winery wine club offers small batch, hand crafted wines that can’t be found any other way. In the end, wine clubs aren’t for everybody. They’re expensive and shipping can be a pain. However, increasingly wine clubs and DTC sales are the only champions of consumer choice in the wine industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my final post on this subject I will discuss why small batch wines matter and how the craft beer boom may actually save the wine industry…if it doesn’t kill it first.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 02:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/what-the-hell-is-a-wine-club-p2/</guid>
        
        <category>wineclub</category>
        
        
        <category>Wine</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yno Wine Trivia</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/yno_trivia_logo_512.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yno Wine Trivia&quot; class=&quot;portfolio-hero-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What “non-existent” wine did Ellen Barkin offer Matt Damon in &lt;em&gt;Oceans 13&lt;/em&gt;? Where does &lt;em&gt;Gruner Veltliner&lt;/em&gt; come from? These questions and more are answered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Brainstorm-Creative-Wine-Trivia/dp/B071Y1HRP1/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-skills&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503377224&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=wine+trivia&quot;&gt;Yno Wine Trivia&lt;/a&gt;. A fun Alexa skill to play with friends or study for WSET, Sommelier, or CSW tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;curiosity-and-study&quot;&gt;Curiosity and Study&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do I learn more about wine?” As a wine educator I’ve encountered this question more times than I can remember. The problem is wine is a daunting subject. I often refer to it as the world‘s 2nd oldest profession. It‘s history, viticulture, and production go back centuries. So, where does one start to get a taste of what it‘s like to learn about wine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From my own journey with wine I’ve found that large part of it’s enjoyment starts with education&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alexa-fied&quot;&gt;Alexa-fied&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voice-enabled digital assistants are fast becoming the next consumer must-have. Amazon’s Alexa is an industry leader. The simple act of asking a question without reaching for a mobile device or tapping a keyboard breaks down barriers for software developers. In addition, Alexa’s built-in trivia skill makes it even easier. I could not build an app like Yno Wine Trivia as fun and compelling without Alexa. Nor could I build it as fast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 01:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/yno-trivia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/yno-trivia/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Software</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
